I was born and raised in North Korea.
ولدت و نشأت في كوريا الشمالية
Although my family constantly struggled against poverty,
على الرغم من أن عائلتي كافحت ضد الفقر
I was always loved and cared for first,
كنت دائماً محبوباً و يعتنى بي أولاً
because I was the only son
لأني كنت الابن الوحيد
and the youngest of two in the family.
و أصغر اثنين في العائلة
But then the great famine began in 1994.
ولكن المجاعة العظمى بدأت في عام ١٩٩٤
I was four years old.
كان عمري ٤ سنوات
My sister and I would go searching for firewood
كنت أذهب و أختي للبحث عن الحطب
starting at 5 in the morning
ونبدأ من الساعة الخامسة صباحاً
and come back after midnight.
و نعود بعد منتصف الليل
I would wander the streets searching for food,
و أمضي في الشوارع بحثاً عن الطعام
and I remember seeing a small child
و أتذكر مشاهدة طفل صغير
tied to a mother's back eating chips,
تحمله أمه على ظهرها يأكل رقائق البطاطا
and wanting to steal them from him.
و كنت أريد سرقتها منه
Hunger is humiliation. Hunger is hopelessness.
الجوع هو الاذلال. الجوع هو فقدان الأمل
For a hungry child, politics and freedom
كطفل جائع، السياسة و الحرية
are not even thought of.
لا يُفكر فيها حتى
On my ninth birthday, my parents
بعيد ميلادي التاسع، والداي
couldn't give me any food to eat.
لم يستطيعوا أن يقدمون إلي طعاماً لآكله
But even as a child, I could feel the heaviness
ولكن حتى كطفل، أستطعت الشعور بالثقل
in their hearts.
في قلوبهم
Over a million North Koreans died of starvation in that time,
أكثر من مليون كوري شمالي ماتوا جوعاً في ذلك الوقت
and in 2003, when I was 13 years old,
وفي عام ٢٠٠٣، عندما كان عمري ١٣ سنة
my father became one of them.
أصبح والدي واحداً منهم
I saw my father wither away and die.
رأيت والدي يذبل و يموت
In the same year, my mother disappeared one day,
وفي نفس السنة، غابت أمي يوماً
and then my sister told me
عندها قالت أختي لي
that she was going to China to earn money,
أنها ستذهب إلى الصين لجني المال،
but that she would return with money and food soon.
و أنها قريباً ستعود بالمال و الطعام
Since we had never been separated,
و لأننا لم ننفصل أبداً
and I thought we would be together forever,
و اعتقدت أننا ستبقى معاً للأبد
I didn't even give her a hug when she left.
لم أقم حتى بضمها عندما رحلت.
It was the biggest mistake I have ever made in my life.
و كان ذلك أكبر خطأ قمت به في حياتي
But again, I didn't know
و لكن مجدداً، لم أكن أعلم
it was going to be a long goodbye.
أنه سيكون وداعاً طويلاً
I have not seen my mom or my sister since then.
ولم أرى أمي و أختي منذ ذلك
Suddenly, I became an orphan and homeless.
فجأة، أصبحت يتيماً و مشرداً
My daily life became very hard,
حياتي اليومية أصبحت صعبة جداً
but very simple.
و لكن بسيطة جداً
My goal was to find a dusty piece of bread in the trash.
كان هدفي ايجاد قطعة من الخبز في سلة المهملات
But that is no way to survive.
ولكن ذلك من أجل البقاء
I started to realize, begging would not be the solution.
بدأت أدرك أن التسول لن يكون الحل
So I started to steal from food carts in illegal markets.
لهذا بدأت بسرقة المطاعم المتنقلة في الأسواق الغير قانونية
Sometimes, I found small jobs
وفي بعض الأحيان كنت أجد وظائف متواضعة
in exchange for food.
مقابل الطعام
Once, I even spent two months in the winter
مرة، قضيت شهرين في الشتاء
working in a coal mine,
بالعمل في منجم فحم حجري
33 meters underground without any protection
٣٣ متر تحت الأرض بدون أي حماية
for up to 16 hours a day.
لمدة تصل إلى ١٦ ساعة في اليوم
I was not uncommon.
لم أكن غير عادي
Many other orphans survived this way, or worse.
العديد من الأيتام نجو بهذه الطريقة، أو أسوأ
When I could not fall asleep from bitter cold
عندما لا أستطيع النوم من البرد القارس
or hunger pains,
أو ألم الجوع
I hoped that, the next morning,
آمل أن الصباح المقبل
my sister would come back to wake me up
أن أختي ستأتي لتوقظني
with my favorite food.
ومعها طعامي المفضل
That hope kept me alive.
هذ الأمل أبقاني حياً
I don't mean big, grand hope.
و لا أعني بذلك الأمل الكبير العظيم
I mean the kind of hope that made me believe
أقصد النوع من الأمل الذي جعلني أؤمن
that the next trash can had bread,
أن سلة المهملات التالية فيها خبزاً
even though it usually didn't.
على الرغم من أنها غالباً لا تحتوي على خبز
But if I didn't believe it, I wouldn't even try,
ولكن إذا كنت لا أؤمن بذلك، لم أكن أحاول حتى
and then I would die.
وعندها سأموت
Hope kept me alive.
الأمل أبقاني حياً
Every day, I told myself,
كل يوم، كنت أقول لنفسي
no matter how hard things got,
مهما أصبحت الأشياء صعبة
still I must live.
مع ذلك يجب أن أعيش
After three years of waiting for my sister's return,
بعد ثلاث سنوات من انتظار عودة أختي
I decided to go to China to look for her myself.
قررت الذهاب إلى الصين للبحث عنها بنفسي
I realized
أدركت
I couldn't survive much longer this way.
أنه لا يمكنني العيش لفترة أطول بهذه الطريقة
I knew the journey would be risky,
كنت أعلم أن الرحلة ستكون خطرة
but I would be risking my life either way.
ولكن كنت سأعرض حياتي للخطر في كلتا الحالتين
I could die of starvation like my father in North Korea,
كان من الممكن أن أموت جوعاً مثل والدي في كوريا الشمالية
or at least I could try for a better life
أو على الأقل أستطيع أن أحاول في سبيل الحصول على حياة أفضل
by escaping to China.
بالهرب إلى الصين
I had learned that many people tried to cross
عرفت أن العديد من الأشخاص حاولوا أن يقطعوا
the border to China in the nighttime to avoid being seen.
الحدود مع الصين في الليل لتجنب أن يراهم أحد
North Korean border guards often shoot and kill people
حرس الحدود الكوريين الشماليين غالباً يرمون بالرصاص و يقتلون الناس
trying to cross the border without permission.
الذين يحاولون قطع الحدود بلا ترخيص
Chinese soldiers will catch
و سوف يقوم الجنود الصينيون بالقبض
and send back North Koreans,
و اعادة ارسال الكوريين الشماليين
where they face severe punishment.
حيث يواجهون العقاب الشديد
I decided to cross during the day,
قررت أن أعبر الحدود في النهار
first because I was still a kid and scared of the dark,
أولا لأني كنت ما أزال طفلاً و أخاف من الظلام
second because I knew I was already taking a risk,
ثانياً لأني كنت أعلم أني أخاطر بحياتي
and since not many people tried to cross during the day,
و لأن العديد من الناس لم تحاول العبور في النهار
I thought I might be able to cross
أعتقدت أنه بامكاني العبور
without being seen by anyone.
بدون أن يشاهدني أحد
I made it to China on February 15, 2006.
دخلت الصين في ١٥ فبراير ٢٠٠٦
I was 16 years old.
كان عمري ١٦ سنة
I thought things in China would be easier,
أعتقدت أن الأمور في الصين ستكون أفضل
since there was more food.
لأن هناك طعام أكثر
I thought more people would help me.
اعتقدت أن هناك أشخاص أكثر سيساعدونني
But it was harder than living in North Korea,
ولكنها الحياة فيها كانت أصعب من كوريا الشمالية
because I was not free.
لأني كنت غير حر
I was always worried about being caught
كنت دائماً قلقاً حول امكانية القبض علي
and sent back.
و اعادة ارسالي
By a miracle, some months later,
و بمعجزة، بعد عدة أشهر
I met someone who was running
قابلت شخصاً كان يدير
an underground shelter for North Koreans,
ملجأً أرضياً للكوريين الشماليين
and was allowed to live there
وكان مسموح لي بالعيش هناك
and eat regular meals for the first time in many years.
و أكل وجبات منتظمة للمرة الأولى منذ عدة سنوات
Later that year, an activist helped me escape China
بآخر تلك السنة، ساعدني ناشط على الهروب من الصين
and go to the United States as a refugee.
و الذهاب إلى الولايات المتحدة كلاجئ
I went to America without knowing a word of English,
ذهبت إلى أمريكا بدون معرفة أي كلمة من الإنجليزية
yet my social worker told me that I had to go to high school.
مع ذلك قال لي مسؤول الخدمة الاجتماعية أن علي الذهاب إلى المدرسة الثانوية
Even in North Korea, I was an F student.
في كوريا الشمالية، كنت طالباً راسباً
(Laughter)
--
And I barely finished elementary school.
و بالكاد أنهيت المرحلة الإبتدائية
And I remember I fought in school more than once a day.
وقد كافحت في المدرسة أكثر من مرة في اليوم
Textbooks and the library were not my playground.
الكتب و المكتبات لم تكن خلفيتي
My father tried very hard to motivate me into studying,
حاول والدي بشدة تحفيزي على الدراسة
but it didn't work.
ولكن هذا لم ينجح
At one point, my father gave up on me.
وذلك لأن والدي يأس مني من جهه
He said, "You're not my son anymore."
وقال: "أنت لست ابني بعد الآن"
I was only 11 or 12, but it hurt me deeply.
كان عمري ١١ أو ١٢ فقط، ولكن هذا أثر كثيراً علي
But nevertheless, my level of motivation
و مع ذلك مستواي من التحفيز
still didn't change before he died.
بقي لم يتغير قبل وفاته
So in America, it was kind of ridiculous
لهذا في أمريكا، كان ذلك سخيفاً نوعاً ما
that they said I should go to high school.
أنهم قالوا أنه يجب علي الالتحاق بالمدرسة الثانوية
I didn't even go to middle school.
لم أكن قد التحقت بالمدرسة المتوسطة حتى
I decided to go, just because they told me to,
قررت الذهاب، لأنهم فقط قالوا لي
without trying much.
بدون أن أحاول كثيراً
But one day, I came home and my foster mother
ولكن في يوم ما، عدت إلى المنزل و أمي بالتبني
had made chicken wings for dinner.
أعدت أجنحة الدجاج للعشاء
And during dinner, I wanted to have one more wing,
وخلال العشاء أردت حبة أخرى من الدجاج
but I realized there were not enough for everyone,
و لكن أعتقدت أنها لا تكفي للجميع
so I decided against it.
و قررت عكس ذلك
When I looked down at my plate,
عندما نظرت إلى صحني
I saw the last chicken wing, that my foster father had given me his.
رأيت آخر حبة من أجنحة الدجاج التي أعطاني إليها أبي بالتبني
I was so happy.
كنت سعيداً جداً
I looked at him sitting next to me.
رأيته جالساً قربي
He just looked back at me very warmly,
و نظر إلي بدفء كبير
but said no words.
بدون أن يتكلم
Suddenly I remembered my biological father.
فجأة تذكرت أبي البيالوجي
My foster father's small act of love
صنيع أبي بالتربية الملئ بالحب
reminded me of my father,
ذكرني بوالدي
who would love to share his food with me
الذي أحب مشاركتي الطعام
when he was hungry, even if he was starving.
عندما كان جائعاً و حتى عندما كان يموت جوعاً
I felt so suffocated that I had so much food in America,
شعرت بالغصة لأنني كنت أحصل على طعام كثير في أمريكا
yet my father died of starvation.
ووالدي مات جوعاً
My only wish that night was to cook a meal for him,
أمنيتي الوحيدة في تلك الليلة هي اعداد وجبة معه
and that night I also thought of what else I could do
و في تلك الليلة أيضاً فكرت بماذا يمكنني العمل أيضاً
to honor him.
لأشرفه
And my answer was to promise to myself
و جوابي كان أن أعاهد نفسي
that I would study hard and get the best education
أن أدرس بجد و أحصل على أفضل تعليم
in America to honor his sacrifice.
في أمريكا تشريفاً لتضحيته
I took school seriously,
و أخذ المدرسة بجد
and for the first time ever in my life,
و للمرة الأولى في حياتي
I received an academic award for excellence,
حصلت على مكافأة أكاديمية بتقدير ممتاز
and made dean's list from the first semester in high school.
و كنت في قائمة العميد من أول فصل دراسي في الثانوية
(Applause)
--
That chicken wing changed my life.
أجنحة الدجاج تلك غيرت حياتي
Hope is personal. Hope is something
الأمل ذاتي. الأمل هو شي
that no one can give to you.
لا يستطيع أحد أن يعطيك إياه
You have to choose to believe in hope.
لديك الخيار بالايمان بالأمل
You have to make it yourself.
يجب أن تصنعه بنفسك
In North Korea, I made it myself.
في كوريا الشمالية، صنعته بنفسي
Hope brought me to America.
الأمل جلبني إلى أمريكا
But in America, I didn't know what to do,
و لكن في أمريكا، لم أكن أعرف ماذا سأفعل
because I had this overwhelming freedom.
وذلك بسبب الحرية الكبيرة التي كانت لدي
My foster father at that dinner gave me a direction,
والدي بالتبني ألهمني الاتجاه في ذلك العشاء
and he motivated me and gave me a purpose
و حفزني و أعطاني الغاية
to live in America.
للعيش في أميركا
I did not come here by myself.
لم آتي إلى هنا بنفسي
I had hope, but hope by itself is not enough.
كان لدي الأمل، لكن الأمل وحده لا يكفي
Many people helped me along the way to get here.
ساعدني الكثير من الناس على طول الطريق للقدوم هنا
North Koreans are fighting hard to survive.
الكوريين الشماليين يحاربون بقوه للنجاة
They have to force themselves to survive,
يجبرون أنفسهم على النجاة
have hope to survive,
لديهم الأمل بالنجاة
but they cannot make it without help.
ولكن لايستطيعون النجاة بلا مساعدة
This is my message to you.
هذه رسالتي اليكم
Have hope for yourself,
كونوا أشخاصاً لديهم الأمل
but also help each other.
و لكن اخدموا بعضكم البعض أيضاً
Life can be hard for everyone, wherever you live.
الحياة من الممكن أن تكون صعبة لكل شخص، أينما تعيش
My foster father didn't intend to change my life.
والدي بالتبني لم يقصد تغيير حياتي
In the same way, you may also change someone's life
و بنفس الطريقة، تستطيع أنت تغيير حياة شخص ما
with even the smallest act of love.
بتعبير بسيط من الحب
A piece of bread can satisfy your hunger,
قطعة من الخبز تستطيع تلبية جوعك
and having the hope will bring you bread
و الأمل يجلب لك الخبز
to keep you alive.
ليبقيك حياً
But I confidently believe that
و لكنني أؤمن بثقة أن
your act of love and caring
تعبيرك عن الحب و العناية
can also save another Joseph's life
يستطيع انقاذ حياة جوزيف آخر
and change thousands of other Josephs
و يغير حياة الآلاف من الأشخاص
who are still having hope to survive.
الذين مازال لديهم الأمل بالنجاة
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
--
Adrian Hong: Joseph, thank you for sharing
أدرين يونج: يوسف، شكراً على مشاركة
that very personal and special story with us.
هذه القصة الشخصية و الخاصة معنا
I know you haven't seen your sister for, you said,
أعرف أنك لم تقابل أختك منذ، كما قلت
it was almost exactly a decade,
أنه تقريباً عقد من الزمن،
and in the off chance that she may be able to see this,
و كفرصة أنها من الممكن أن تشاهد ذلك
we wanted to give you an opportunity
نريد اعطائك الفرصة
to send her a message.
لإرسال رسالة لها
Joseph Kim: In Korean?
بالكورية ؟
AH: You can do English, then Korean as well.
بالانجليزية، بعدها بالكورية
(Laughter)
--
JK: Okay, I'm not going to make it any longer in Korean
حسناً، لن أقوم بالاطالة بالكوري
because I don't think I can make it
لأني لا أعتقد اني أستطيع فعل ذلك
without tearing up.
بدون أن تدمع عيناي
Nuna, it has been already 10 years
نونا، قد أكملت ١٠ سنوات
that I haven’t seen you.
ولم أقابلك منذ ذلك
I just wanted to say
فقط أريد أن أقول
that I miss you, and I love you,
أنني اشتقت إليك و أنني أحبك
and please come back to me and stay alive.
و من فضلك عودي إلي و ابقي حية
And I -- oh, gosh.
و أنا -- يا إلهي
I still haven't given up my hope to see you.
لم أفقد الأمل بلقائك
I will live my life happily
سأعيش حياتي بسعادة
and study hard
و سأدرس بجد
until I see you,
حتى ألقاك
and I promise I will not cry again.
و أعدك أنني لن أبكي بعد ذلك
(Laughter)
--
Yes, I'm just looking forward to seeing you,
نعم، أتمنى فقط لقائك
and if you can't find me,
و اذا لم تستطيعي العثور علي
I will also look for you,
سأبحث عنك أيضاً
and I hope to see you one day.
و آمل أن ألقاك يوماً ما
And can I also make a small message to my mom?
هل أستطيع القاء رسالة قصيرة لأمي ؟
AH: Sure, please.
بالتأكيد، من فضلك
JK: I haven't spent much time with you,
لم أقضي وقتاً طويلاً معك
but I know that you still love me,
و لكنني أعلم أنك مازلت تحبينني
and you probably still pray for me
و ربما مازلت تدعين لي
and think about me.
و تفكرين بي
I just wanted to say thank you
فقط أريد أن أقول لك شكراً
for letting me be in this world.
لجعلي في هذا العالم
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
--